howdy this is jim rutt and this is the
jim rutt show
[Music]
this is a current episode currents are
shorter and less heavily produced than
our full-length episodes and generally
focus
on a single topic as always links to
books
articles and organizations mentioned are
available on the episode page at
jimrudshow.com that's jimrutshow.com
today's guest on this current episode is
tyson yonkoporta how you going jim no
howdy today
usually looks howdy how dare that i
i picked that up when i was living in
idaho out in uh
actually sheepherder country and all the
local people said howdy and i picked it
up and i've used it ever since and when
i lived in boston people looked at me
like i was the man from the moon when i
said howdy but hey
that's the way it goes howdy tyson howdy
tyson's an academic an arts critic and a
researcher who is a member of the
appalach clan
in far northern queensland he carves
traditional indigenous tools and weapons
out of wood mostly and also works as a
senior lecturer in
indigenous knowledges at deakin
university in melbourne
and he lives in melbourne at least most
of the time
tyson's been on the show twice
previously where we have dug into his
remarkable new book
sand talk and as always we'll have a
link to sand talk on the episode page at
jimrutshow.com
if you care about the future of humanity
read this
book in fact jim root says
read sand talk or i'll kick your ass
how about that for a blurb that's that's
an endorsement that's going on the cover
in the next edition that one
i'll tell you you know send that send
that one to your publisher and say that
that
in the next printing uh that's got to be
on the on the back cover
yeah now seriously people this is not
only a must read book for anybody that
cares about the future of humanity
but it's also a great work of art i'm
serious about this it is not
linear it's not a list of the 13 things
you can do to save the planet
it's a beautiful weaving of tyson's
personal story the story of the people
of australia the people of the world the
craziness of the world
complexity indigenous knowledge all
woven together into an astounding
tapestry
if you read one book this year read sand
talk
but now let's get into the topic of
today uh since
i read the book and had those two
wonderful conversations with tyson
one idea from the book in particular has
just
pulled at me and i just keeps pulling me
back and making me look at it again and
again so i reached out to
tyson said let's just talk about this
one topic and that's a topic
which he calls humans as the custodial
species of the earth so what did you
what do you mean by that
well it's i mean it's uh it's just a
foundational
understanding in in most of our um
aboriginal cultures and torres strait
islander cultures in australia
and uh yeah it's most of our
um our creation stories
you know culminate in in uh
human beings being given this role of
humans being past this knowledge
and this law from um creator entities
of how to be in the world and what your
role is
and how you're maintaining this uh sort
of custodial relation
uh with all of creation yeah of course
the christians
uh christian canon also has that you
know when uh when they kick adam and eve
out of uh
uh uh garden of eden you know good old
yahweh says and you will have dominion
over
everybody and it's you know kind of uh
ugly frankly yeah
i'm not sure i i like that model of a
custodial species
uh do you have a better one yeah well
the dominion's a different thing
i mean even the word custodial is about
as close as you can get in english to it
it's just um
you know it brings to mind ideas of
custody
and you know like you're holding
capturing
trapping this nature you know and that's
not quite the idea but
most people have an idea of what
custodianship
is and it's you know it's a bit of a
light hand
and something that has to be you know
deeply considered
and sort of has to be governed by
um sort of more natural natural law than
anything
else and what is it you think that
allows or permits
or demands maybe is a better word that
humans be that custodial species could
it be
you know again i do a lot of work in
cognitive science cognitive neuroscience
and
there does sure seem to be a pretty
bright line between the
uh mental and reasoning capabilities of
homo sapiens and all the other species
you know we're the only one that
has uh what we call general intelligence
you know given enough time and enough
paper we can figure out almost
anything and that's very different than
the other animals is that what uh makes
us
uh the ones who are the custodians or is
there something
well about humans if you look at um
most of the other beings in the system
you know in a complex dynamic system um
they're largely concerned with their
niche and the relation of that niche to
uh to to all you know to the other
things around it
you know um you know with the exception
of some things like
you know mycelium and all that sort of
thing which tends to be a big sort of
uh underground almost internet you know
that goes through the entire system
and you know communicates things in real
time right across say a forest or
whatever
so i mean but you know mycelia they
don't have opposable thumbs you know
they don't have symbolic reasoning and
they don't have
uh you know discrete memory they do have
a chemical memory which is interesting
mycelium are very very interesting but
they they don't have uh uh they lack a
lot
in the ability to generalize and look at
the really big picture
and and also to uh work in to even
understand the idea of depth of time
you know i was looking at my dog the
other day and he's a pretty damn smart
dog as dogs go
uh but he you know has definite
limitations for instance in this uh
place we're renting in pittsburgh for uh
uh
a few weeks here waiting for a
grandchild to show up
uh i walk we walk the dog around the
block and he has not yet figured out
that the we go out the back door through
the alley and then around the city block
he hasn't figured out yet that the front
door and the back door are somehow
related but
but you know humans have the capability
to do that very easily a four-year-old
figures that out in one day
yeah and well i guess they're um they're
specialists aren't they
uh a lot of animals are kind of
specialists whereas we're
we're more generalists yep but anyway
there's clearly a difference in our
capability and so hey we
you know we're the ones who are the only
ones that really can be
responsible well we can we can see like
our minds are
such that we're able to perceive um
the entire system you know if we really
do put our minds to work the way
they were designed to be um we we can
perceive an entire
complex system but we can also perceive
the systems beyond
that system and the way they interact
you know so i guess it's that unique
uh capacity that that you know the
you know we would say we've been given
by the sort of hero ancestors and
you know the creation entities um
we've been given those gifts you know
particularly so that we can be that
custodial species
you know so there's a there's a dreaming
story in western australia they
you know they talk about there was a big
meeting
you know everything all the trees the
plants the animals
and you know humans were in there where
they were sitting down at that moment of
creation
um to decide who who the carers for
everything were going to be
so that's the language they use now that
they call it the carers of everything
um so who was going to care for all of
this and oversee it
and you know it went through each of the
traits of each animal and the trees were
like well we can't move around
and you know and the kangaroo came
really close apparently
but um he just had these shitty little
arms you know
and they weren't quite going to do it so
yeah it ended up being the human beings
you know it had that capacity and the
hands are really important
you know they have a really big
significance um
spiritual significance in our cultures
the hands and for human beings all
around the
world that's what you see on the cave
walls you know and that rock
art yep is always happening it goes all
over the world i've seen them i've seen
where they people put their hands
against the wall and then apparently
they would take
uh paint put it in their mouth and spit
it out to produce those patterns that
was a common way they would do it
you know a handsome you know remarkable
and of course they
you know they're the things that allow
us to have that haptic cognition
you know where a tool becomes recognized
in our brain as an extension of our arm
you know they're the way we um you know
interact with the world
yeah and also tools uh i you know i've
worked with other people on
on a a theory of linguistics it may not
be true but it's possible that it is
which is that we learned how to make
multi-part tools before we develop
syntactical language
and it turned and it turns out based on
our analysis the tool making is
in many ways similar to syntactic
language in that
it's not rigid you can make the parts in
a different order
but you have to put them together in the
same way to have the tools so it has
that both the
uh kind of requirement and freedom
of language and that may well have been
that the mental capacity for building
tools
is what we were able to leverage into
our
even more powerful uh tool of language
and potentially the language may have
developed out of need to sing
um it's just a is an interesting little
thing to think about you know because um
you often see
like when your your grandchild is born
there you know and you watch
you watch them grow um you'll see kids
are always
like they're singing before they can
speak they're trying to sing you know
it's like one of the first things we try
and do
um you know the same way they try and
run
before they can even stand up um
so i and i think the singing is
important because that's part of your
that's how you um you encode all those
relations
of being the custodial species is is
through
uh ceremonies um you know
and you sing all those stories but you
sing
like i mentioned to you before about the
increase ceremonies
and the increased ceremonies are about
um not increasing the size of the system
that you're a custodian of
but increasing the combinatorials within
the system
so you're increasing i love that
increasing the connections between
things
you know so and you actually sing those
connections
you sing them into being and you're
taught this from a really
young age so i was talking to a samoan
someone followed yesterday and he was
talking about
um there's this concept they have um
like their word for warm data i guess
you'd call it
is is i think it's va is what he said
and um it's it's an actual
thing it's a force an energy it's a
substance but it is the um
it's the thing that exists between
things in the relation between things
and he was telling tell me about the
five stages that you go through and
coming to
increased knowledge of of that um that
summer and warm data thing and and it's
uh the first one is when you're very
young when you're
just starting to stand um and right the
way through when you're a toddler and
you're a young kid
your mother will take you and put you um
there on the beach
and get you to pay attention to your
feet on the sand
and that var between your feet and the
sand that
um that uh relation between them
but right at the edge of the water so
then the waves come up and wash over
your
your feet and so then you're seeing the
connection between those
three things you know that that relation
that you have
and that's the earliest you know
simplest form of that
um and so all of your all of your
cultural expression
um all of your ceremony ritual
and just the day you live the way you
live from day to day
it's all about um working with those
working with that in between you know
which is just as real as as the things
themselves you know the connections
between things
yeah it's very real yeah
absolutely and indeed that's you know
part of the modern thinking of
complexity which you and i both
enjoy studying as i often will say as a
shorthand to help people understand the
idea of complexity
you know older science reduction of
science can be thought of as the study
of the dancers
while complexity can be thought of the
study of the dance
right the interrelationship between the
dancers right and the dance
is as real in fact i would argue in some
sense
more real than the dance right than the
dancers
i mean what is life but a dance of
chemicals right
uh you know what is a society but a
dance of people
and stuff uh and so the the
relationships and the dynamics
are to my mind critical which actually
brings me to the first quote i'm going
to read from your book which i'd love to
get your comment it's a perfect time for
it
oh by the way just to show you how
central custodial species is to your
book i
use my little tool i have and i
discovered that custodial species
appears 12 times in your book
so it is actually a very important
concept
i found that authors don't often know
those kinds of things isn't that
interesting right
anyway here's uh tyson on uh one of his
earlier not the first uh
writings in the book on custodial
species the book by the way is saying
talk read it or i'll kick your ass
uh here we go creation is in a constant
state of motion
and we must move with it as the
custodial species
or we will damage the system and doom
ourselves
nothing can be held accumulated stored
every unit requires velocity and
exchange in a stable system
or it will stagnate this applies to
economic and social systems
as well as natural ones that's
it isn't that good yeah it's it's that
accumulation i think you know when
when you do you have that game in the
states past the parcel
no it's where there's like a okay in
australia there's this thing and they i
think they do it in the uk too
at a birthday party or whatever there's
like a little present
like a gift but it's got you know about
20 layers of wrapping around it and all
the kids sit in a circle
and they have to pass the parcel and
they take off one one layer at a time
until finally the one who unwraps the
gift they get to keep the gift
right and you see it they usually have
music playing and they're doing it
really fast and everyone's really
excited
but there's always that one fucking kid
you know
when he gets the parcel he just holds it
he's there and holds it and everyone's
getting really uncomfortable and
everyone's trying to get him to pass it
on he won't pass it on
and there's just always that prick you
know
in this you know yeah he's a game he's a
gamester he figures out the game he
figures
he's the game motherfucker
hey i just um i was thinking the other
day i was saying you should get game b
hats
and then um i know i popped into my head
that um
you know those maga hats yeah yeah that
mega is almost an anagram of um
game a
surprisingly similar kind of a
degenerate version of game a for fucking
idiots right
uh unfortunately the idiot players of
game a are less dangerous than the smart
players of gaming yeah
right that's one of the principles you
know
is interaction in all the nodes in that
system
there has to be this constant dynamic
interaction
you know it's it's resources materials
matter
information particularly you know it has
to
it's all information really right yeah
you don't have
one node that's like collecting all that
information for itself and holding it
you know storing it or that energy you
know it's the same with money
exactly money this actually just caused
the thought to jump into my head
people who listen to the show know that
i'm generally speaking a skeptic
of bitcoin and uh other similar kinds of
cryptocurrencies
and as it turns out if you look at
those money systems quantitatively you
find that there's almost no velocity in
them
people never use them to buy anything
right it's basically speculators
hoarders people sitting on nest eggs
and there's no life to it there's no
velocity in exchange
right and uh while i can in my money
system
uh which you can find on
uh youtube i have a
90 90-minute talk on uh uh dividend
money and alternative the central
banking
uh partial reserve uh fractional reserve
banking money
uh we the one of the key things in it is
to make sure the system has
lots of velocity and lots of exchange
and lots of dynamism
uh you know a money system where people
just sit on their ass on top of their
money that's
you know that's sick actually and that's
really what bitcoin is yeah
and that's um i mean that's what we
mentioned i think in the last show was
i was talking about that uh that we have
this
increased paradigm as opposed to a
growth paradigm
and that's exactly it you know it's it's
having that velocity
um you know within the system of of of
information value you know um
objects yeah trade has to go like that
you know
um so yeah i think that's what
some sort of qualitative easing might
look like instead of quantitative easing
would be
you know increasing the velocity of the
dollar and improving the health of your
system yep
and there's ways that if our velocity
has been falling too it's been falling
for a number of years
that's one of the things i personally
follow as part of my work on monetary
economics
now let's turn from this beautiful view
to the world we live in today
where i would say that so-called
civilization
is not doing a good job as a custodial
species
and until very recently didn't he wasn't
even aware of the fact
that it had that role you know it's
still rushing towards the cliff
and at a break break next speed
and either will overpopulate the earth
we'll deplete our soils we'll kill the
uh micro uh species that live in the
soils that make
uh you know plant life uh viable
or we'll cook ourselves or we'll uh be
so crowded together and and
dealing with each other in such corrupt
ways that we'll have pandemic after
pandemic
we don't seem to give a fuck about being
the custodial species anymore at least
so-called civilization doesn't there was
i
and i think um i think
these things happen periodically
i think in in human populations
particularly after a cataclysm of some
kind
um you know people experiment with these
unsustainable systems
there's a place i live for a year in far
north queensland
called kuranda and kuranda is um
it's it's a new landscape it's only like
10 000 years old because
you know it was there was a big volcanic
cataclysm there
and it ended up developing into a rain
forest
and anyway there's a really big story
there um
and so it's not as old as most of the
stories in australia it's a new one
because it's a new landscape you know
um that's very interesting yeah and it's
this uh
this big rainbow serpent sort of
travels periodically down uh down to the
sea and then up onto the table land
along a waterway now that uh
the ocean there in that coast um
there was this kind of rare
spiral shell that the people there
started using as a fungible token
back then so they were like using it as
a a currency
basically so it was an experiment with
money
um so they were they were using that to
you know
to store value in their trades but there
were all these problems because
all of a sudden um things weren't moving
there was no velocity
there were people who were like
gathering these shells in piles and just
sort of keeping them you know
and it's it slowed things down and you
know people were getting sick and
things were going wrong and there were
lots of fights and this story
is the story of the first heist because
their rainbow snake had come up out of
the ocean
and he'd have a lot of these shells
stuck in his scales
and so he was ambushed by these
blackbird people you know going up the
hill
and they dropped a log on him and
murdered him right there now um the
rainbow snake is a a really big
one of those big creator beings you know
in our world view one of
the ones i was mentioning before one of
the really big really important creative
beings is really central to
most aboriginal cultures all over
australia so it's a terrible thing that
they'd murdered
uh him and uh and after that people
decided to
abandon that that currency and that that
system because it was just um
you know it was obviously going to
destroy everything and the warning of
that story is that
you know you'll destroy creation itself
if you're doing that
if you're not sharing freely and having
constant uh
movement in whatever trading system you
have
yeah you have to have the dynamism there
it's kind of you know it has to work for
everybody right
why is that so hard why is civilization
not able to
understand that it's a very interesting
question yeah and you actually propose a
reason and i'm gonna quote
uh uh actually let's let's wait till a
little later for that one because
here's one that i'd love you to
explicate for me as i was going through
the book again
uh for for today's talk i said this is
interesting but i'm not
not sure i understand it let me ask the
man himself
uh you say we are the custodians of this
reality
and the arrow of time is not an
appropriate model for a custodial
species to
operate from what do you mean by that
damn interesting words but i'm not quite
sure what it means
that was behind a lot of the sort of
just little thought experiments i've
been doing um
with the first and second laws of
thermodynamics
and the idea that that maybe the the
second law is is not the most
appropriate model of time
um not the most productive one and um
you know maybe a better one if we're
looking at um a whole heap of
vast complex you know overlapping
interacting dynamic systems that may be
the first law of
thermodynamics um might be worth looking
at
as a as an alternative model of time
because i guess the the arrow of time
you know as it's been created
is um is very much came come out of uh
print-based cultures you know they
developed uh develop print in order to
try and control the story of the past
you know so they they have printed
history and say well this is the version
of your history
and we're showing progress here because
things were really bad and dark and
terrible in the past and
now they're better and every day is
better therefore tomorrow will be better
you know um and so then you know they
write contracts to try and control the
future as well
and they end up you know making these
civilizations fit onto that
uh that that arrow of time and and
therefore that illusion of uh
progress and you know i think that that
illusion of progress and that um that
sort of wrong
story uh of progress that that uh big
lie
um i i think that's um that's the cause
of a lot of our destruction i mean we're
all trapped on this arrow of time and
just
speeding towards the precipice you know
exactly this is such game a heading for
the cliff
you know i think it's that's a simple
explanation of it i kind of go into it a
bit more in the book
you know some of the ideas and then
later i found out that charles darwin
had the same idea when he was messing
around with physics
and of course you know physicists the
hardcore physicists
uh many of them not all but i would say
a majority at this stage
time believe time is an illusion
actually
and that there may not actually be any
time and maybe everything happens
simultaneously and
uh time is something that we impose upon
the structure of the universe isn't that
a weird thought right yeah
yeah well i know a lot of um a lot about
like really really
senior um law people clever people we
call them
um the way they the way they talk and
interact with the world is is definitely
on a completely different model of time
there's a scholar called um christine
black
and she wrote a book about indigenous
jurisprudence
called the land as the source of the law
she was telling me the other day that
she's come to the conclusion that um
that those old people
uh live in a state of quantum
was how she put it well they could hop
around between you know with our
you know aren't what's called uh
non-localism again something that
physics
shows actually does exist in fact i
would say
most all physicists believe that this
universe is non-local meaning that
uh things can go from a to b without
being anywhere in between
well talk about in the book a lot
um tell his story and he's got um uh
i think about yeah half a dozen of the
symbols in the book are his
sand talk symbols that he wanted to
share with the world
and when he first showed me those it was
more than just those there were about
there must have been two or three
hundred symbols you showed me all in one
day
um it nearly made my head burst but he
um
he he was blowing my mind and i he kept
saying things that
you know like he knew all about my life
somehow
you know and but and he was referring to
things future events as they were
happening
now and so and he said ah that place
where you're going tomorrow
like i didn't know where i was going i
was actually flying out from i was in
the northern territory there
and i was going to be flying all the way
down to the bottom of australia to the
snowy mountains
and i was going to be right up on the
top that snowy mountain there
near the snowy river you know he didn't
know that
he didn't know i was flying out and
going there the next day um
but i hadn't told him anyway and he said
ah that place you're going tomorrow
you need to listen to this yatindi song
because there's a song line
in there and you'll find that song line
um so that's it's called
timeless land that song you need to
listen to that and then you need to
follow that uh
that song line all the way down to the
ocean
and you need to draw these symbols in
the sand there
and draw it right up for on the beach
there and and the big wave will come up
and
and and wash that out to the sea and
then i was laughing at him and i went
are you
like i thought he was a charlatan you
know because uh yothi indi is a band
from um
uh the northern territory and i was like
ah what he doesn't know is that i'm
going to be flying down to the bottom of
the
continent tomorrow he doesn't know where
i'm going to be and so i just dismissed
it and i thought
he's a silly silly person and
yes i was up on that mountain and i was
just i was talking to a
law man there like a senior lawman you
know initiated into the bigger knowledge
and all that
and he said well when those old people
you've got to do what they say and i
said yeah but i'm not in the northern
territory and he went well
just listen to the song anyway so we've
got it up on youtube
there and listen to it and it was um
and the the early right towards the
start of the song the
lyrics are um from the edge of the
mountain down through the valley down
where the snowy river flows
follow the water down to the ocean bring
back the memory
um oh dear he had you
had me so it turns out that those uh you
don't know people from
right up north in australia had visited
that place
and sat down with the old people there
and they knew that song line and they'd
written it into one of their songs
and i'm like wow yeah and he always
talking about future things
in present tense or even sometimes past
tense
like they've already happened you know
like he's narrating something he's
already seen
and and i've never seen that that old
man sleep
you know i've camped with him that many
times never once seen him go to sleep
he's just always there in the same spot
in the morning fully clothed
looks like he hasn't i've never seen him
go to the toilet
i don't know i don't know what's going
on with him it's um
it's terrifying sometimes yeah it sounds
like gandalf the wizard is part of the
ring
that's right he never sleeps and as you
now that you mentioned it that i
can't hear them ever saying he took a
shit either
that's it so you know interesting i mean
that's just
that's campfire sort of stories to scare
small children with i guess
but um you know it's an interesting
thought the the possibility that um
you know our minds can uh can exist
you know out of linear time in that way
another thought
i just had about time stimulated by this
conversation which is
uh you know kind of multifaceted which
is
uh game a or our status quo world has
distorted time in an
extraordinarily dangerous way uh
you know you've if you listen to my show
you've heard me talk about that the
inner engine of game a
is the quest for short-term money on
money return
and how is money on money returned
denominated
by interest rates and what is the
thing about interest rates they're
exponential which means
that if it's ten percent interest the
principal keeps growing
exponentially over time and if you turn
that around into a so-called discount
rate and say what is uh a hundred
dollars worth
in a hundred years the answer is almost
zero if you assume a ten percent
uh interest rate and so uh time
uh in game a in financial terms in a
world driven by money
on money return causes the future to
essentially disappear so nobody cares
about it
yeah and that is that is why
we are not able to uh uh
do our duty as a custodial species as if
you're if you are operating
under the inner engine of money on money
return
which by its debt very definition when
it's uh based on debt money
uh has an exponential discounting of the
future such as
such that the economic measure of the
future is essentially zero it's the
snake eating its tail yeah exactly you
know that
um that that um foundational myth
of civilization the auroboros the worm
orables
have that symbol there it always
terrifies me because they call it a
symbol of infinity but how's that
infinity is just gonna eat himself
until he's just ahead you notice also a
zero right yeah that's it
no it's um it's a zero or some game i
guess
yeah though it doesn't have to be
especially if we uh and remember that
distinction between
increase and growth or i would sometimes
call it the
the growth into the microcosm versus the
growth into the macrocosm
right it doesn't hurt the earth to be
ever more intricate
uh let's say let's think of engraving
our engravings become more intricate we
don't consume more
wood when we do that but we add a lot
more value to the world right
that's a that's a really good metaphor
yeah i think that's
that's what i think that's what i think
of is increase and
growth is oh i i'm going to do kind of
shitty engravings but i'm going to do a
whole bunch of them right
versus one very intricate very beautiful
very
integrated engraving and if we can
change our mindset
towards richness in terms of detail
and connection and dynamics and away
from piling up
shit right uh you know the idea that you
know
you know the worst idea in game a is he
who dies with the most toys wins
right there's there's a there's a
caution though like
i mean you really really do have to know
your stuff
you know because of that um that sort of
you know butterfly effect of tinkering
with um complex systems you know
uh you do an intervention over here and
and
you you it's very difficult to predict
or anticipate
you know which way that's going to go
you do some good over here and something
bad happens over there
um over that place i was talking about
before
you know at corander when i was
traveling up to there i was traveling
from right down
right down in the south see coriander is
the the end of one of those big song
lines
um for the platypus story and i was down
at the start of that story at a place
called naron
lake in western new south wales and and
that story starts with a
a a water rat and a duck
doing the wrong thing and mating when
they shouldn't be mating you know
um god damn it i hate when that is
interesting
because scientists have found both water
rat and duck dna in the platypus
how the hell does that happen anyway so
um
yeah i was following that song line but
then this um
this old lady this law woman clever
woman uh called me up
and you have to do what they say when
they tell you it's it's really hard
i mean you don't have to i mean you can
dodge them if you want but
you won't get asked to do anything else
and you won't they won't share anything
with you again
so i um had to do what she said and
there'd been a big flood in brisbane
in southern queensland there and
and uh a huge flood all the city was
flooded this was about 10 years ago
and all the old people the old
aboriginal people
in in the brisbane area were having
respiratory problems
um there and they were attributing it to
a
um a disturbance in spirit in a place in
the mangroves
and um yeah
the the fruit bat is a really important
medicine for that respiratory
problem so this old lady had identified
that as a disturbance in a fruit bat
place and so she sent me there and it's
at a place called hendra
and so i was standing in the mangrove
swamp and looking across the highway
and there was a horse stud there and
then all the penny dropped for me
because um
um there's a thing in australia called
the hendra virus
and the hendra virus was something
that's
that um started in horses and spread
from the horses to the fruit bat and i
realized that i was a ground zero for
that
spreading of that virus it's like rabies
the fruit
bats go nuts and then they bite people
and then the people get that virus you
know
um so they kind of had it contained
there
apparently um anyway so i'm there
at that site ground zero for the hendra
virus and i so i
i did the the ritual things and called
out the words that the old lady had
given me
and um and all these fruit bats that
were roosting and this is thousands
roosting in the mangroves
they'll just burst up into the air and
they started their migration north early
too early in the season you know and the
idea was that they'd take that bad
spirit away
with them anyway that sounds like a nice
intervention all the old people
you know i i know i heard the story that
they were all getting better and the
respiratory problems had passed
and so i kept driving north because i
was on my way up to the end of that song
line they're up in kuranda
so it's a about a 3 000 kilometer
journey all up um so i drove all the way
up there and took my time
and then you know so i camped there and
i was having breakfast one morning
and i heard on the radio that there'd
been an outbreak of hendra virus in
where i was you know and it had never
spread that far north before but um
you know so i kind of i saw that you
know there was this custodial role
sort of manipulating the system somehow
um you know for good but then you know
it had big knock-on effects that spread
right across the continent
um you know so i'm i'm really careful
i try to be careful um with everything
that i do now
you know if i'm taking on custodial
roles
you know um in any system and of course
that's the things we do learn in uh
complexity science and in
our game b work i make this point again
and again and again
the ability to predict the unfolding of
a complex system when you tinker with it
is quite limited
right and so uh
one must proceed empirically and
experimentally i would argue
at least you know make make probe
changes see what happens wait a bit
make another change oops that one didn't
work out so well
try something else uh and you know
that's the danger of ideology right when
people come with this book
that says you must do all of these
things everyone every jot and tittle
uh you can almost be sure that they're
wrong and unfortunately if they
you know think of marxist leninism as an
example of that
right or some of this new post-modernist
uh crazy shit right if you you know
followed all their prescriptions you
could well just uh
really put civilization uh far off its
uh reasonable track
uh you know with very little ability to
recover by following
uh some uh ideological or utopian vision
too far without taking a
a you know a live experimental and
reaction you know action reaction adjust
uh approach yeah yeah um
i think a lot of you know
we we have all these plans you know
people always asking what's your vision
of the future all these kinds of things
and we're supposed to like design the
future you know
based on a very limited you know map of
what we can see
and i think um a lot of times it's it's
it's got to be a bit more
dynamic than that you know you have to
allow for emergence
you you have to um basically
you know be a caretaker of all the
conditions in the system
uh that will produce the emergence of um
of you know solutions and and changes in
the system
um and and that's all you can do you
know i think if you're
like a more like a gardener right yeah
that's just in
exactly well that's a good transition
point to my next quote
from the book uh this is tyson again
i made a pointed parrying shield out of
fountain potential wood while thinking
about all this
to represent the protection needed while
navigating the space between the
tangible
and intangible worlds that custodial
species
must engage with yeah well
you know i i can um often i'll use the
metaphor of theory and practice
to talk about those um tangible and
intangible worlds
you know so you have to engage with that
a world of
abstract knowledge um and i guess that's
almost a place where you can do safe to
fail
experiments you know what i mean um yeah
you know before you you you do something
you've got to um so i talk about it in
terms of
that metaphor is the language of spirit
so you're translating you know tangible
uh phenomena and um you know things
uh situations you t translating those
into
into an abstract metaphor and then
you're manipulating those in abstract
space
you know and then you complete that that
feedback loop there between those two
worlds by bringing them back into this
world
and that's pretty much how ceremony and
ritual works
you know and if you think about it
that's what mathematics is
mathematics is is translating you know
tangible
uh systems into uh intangible symbols
and metaphors
and um you know manipulating those in
that abstract space and then
you know finding solutions that you can
bring back across into the real world
yeah particularly certainly in
mathematical physics that's the case
maybe less so in abstract mathematics
where some of those guys just pride
themselves in living in the intangible
oh this doesn't have any application why
the hell will i think about that the
problem you have to complete that loop
you have to complete the loop between
the tangible and intangible
otherwise you know yeah i mean i talk
about the problems that that can
create you know uh in the mind
um and that a lot of education is set up
like that
you know to just be sitting in the in
the practical space or just be sitting
in the
the theoretical and never the twenties
you'll meet
and you're yeah that's and it seems like
close to the idea of wisdom is that
dance between the two yeah right well
real learning is
is an act of creation it's so we talk
about so
we talk about that in terms of that
being so the word we'd use for that
today is turn around so a turnaround
event is is that act of creation
and that's like an interaction between
those two worlds
and there has to be a feedback work loop
happening between that world of spirit
or abstract
and um you know tangible
you know physical reality and that needs
to be uh
kept constantly in motion so in learning
that's like this miniature creation
event that happens
you know in your neural processes uh
when you're closing that loop
and it really sparks joy but um
you know uh the opposite happens if
you're just sitting in one or the other
it's you end up with boredom and boredom
pretty much
is it causes brain damage it's a
terrible thing
yeah that's one thing i can say i
haven't i don't know if i've ever been
bored in my life i always find some shit
to get into
right yeah well you know when you went
to school you were
still able to carry knives around on
your belt the eggs are different
exactly yeah indeed
unfortunately and that brings us to our
final topic uh before we wrap up here
uh this is again another quote on this
right on target
uh carrying knives on your belt what
would it mean to reverse this
domesticated state
you talked about how humans had become
self-domesticated over domesticated
particularly in the advanced
so-called advanced world let's use
so-called
uh it would take centuries to transition
from human domestication
and recover our exceptional physical
and mental powers as a custodial
species let's talk about this
over domestication god damn it and what
are some of the things that we as
individuals and societies
ought to do to get ourselves back to
having the physical and mental powers to
be
a responsible custodial species
ah you know a minor top
a small little time i used to think i
had the answer to that but i'm i'm
i'm just fine over the last couple of
years i'm just becoming increasingly
domesticated myself
um yeah
uh yeah you know it's a hard one but
it's it's about um
it's about being embedded in a habitat
you know whatever your habitat is you
know having your awareness
um on all of the interrelated things in
that habitat
you know as much as possible you know
like
paying attention knowing what the
weather is doing and the patterns that
you're seeing in the weather
seeing that you know when this the when
this tree is flowering
these things always have also happen you
know in that season
uh going around around even if you're
living in a city
you know uh looking at what the pigeons
are doing
you know the hawks and eagles that are
nesting up in uh skyscrapers
you know when when are they nesting when
are they mating or all those kinds of
things
but then also you know but bringing that
out into
i think the example i use in the the
the book is that you know when the tea
tree is flowering
i know i can get uh lychees and cherries
at the supermarket
you know so um it's it's finding all
those connections and extending your
awareness out
and actually trying to interact
you know naturally as a node in that
complex dynamic system
you know um as much as possible
um you know and follow those principles
of interaction we were talking about
before where you're
uh you have that velocity happening in
your exchange of uh
information and energy and resources
you know um that you have these
happening in dynamic relation with with
the communities that you're in
human and non-human communities um and i
guess if you're living like that
and being like that then you're your
your
consciousness is changing your your mind
is is sort of um
um it's involved in this
act of increase and i guess that's
that's the best we can do for now
um but try and keep some memory alive
try and and and notice the illusions
that are around you and mark those
things as illusions
and um try and keep yourself behaving in
some way
that you can retain some kind of memory
of what it is to be human
when all of this uh comes down because
it is coming down
you know this civilization is collapsing
and um
and when it does you're going to want to
be able to move
with the habitat and the communities and
the massive changes that are happening
you're going to need to be able to adapt
and um if you want to thrive
and and that's a that's about it at this
stage
um that's about all that most of us can
do
yeah and some of us have the opportunity
to at least
try to maintain our connections to our
roots as you know i
continue to hunt and butcher my own deer
and uh in a pinch i could butcher a cow
if i had too
right probably not not as good as a
professional butcher but i can do it
uh can grow my own food my wife better
than me by far
she's a master gardener uh you know play
with the soil
if you have the opportunity uh you know
as you say notice the world because the
world is gonna strike back
mother nature bats last right that's it
i have a stepdaughter she's like just
13 years old and you know um
yeah i made a a blow gun
you know had a piece of um pvc pipe and
and um and some nails you know so we
made all these blow darts and
um and so she could practice with those
and
it was a deadly shot and we're talking
about it in terms of
you know urban foraging if it comes to
that
you know um because you know all these
run on the supermarkets that happen when
we're in lockdown
you know with coronavirus and that sort
of thing it's like we might not be able
to get meat
one week so you're gonna have to go out
and knock some of these pigeons or some
of the possums that are running around
with your blow gun and uh yeah so we'll
have mid
um yeah and it's we're just about to
move on to knife throwing next
that's the that's the next skill she's
gonna pick up
yeah yeah i remember i was i became
obsessed with knife throwing when i was
about 12.
and uh bought a set of knife throwing
knives got pretty good at it actually it
was a lot of fun because you know you
have to
learn how to get the rotations just
right and all this sort of stuff
uh quite cool i would uh you know
commend you to teach your daughter that
excellent skill
and then all the women and girls in my
house have um you know traditional
aboriginal women's fighting sticks that
i've made for
them and so uh there's been a big spike
in home invasions in uh
in melbourne recently with all the
lockdowns and all that sort of thing
with the coronavirus so uh
but we feel pretty safe here i'm pretty
sure my women will be able to protect me
that's a good thing right that's a very
good thing well
uh tyson i think we're going to wrap it
up here uh you know i think this as
always has been an exceedingly
interesting conversation
and all you people out there go read
sand talk
by tyson yonka porter or i'll kick your
ass
it's been fun and we managed to get
through the whole thing without
sexually assaulting any megafauna in a
thought experiment which uh
yeah yeah fucking at the moment you're
never going to live that down
yeah i'm not i'm not trying to see the
author anymore
or tyson the thinker it's you know you
fuck one mammoth
and that's it yeah
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
jared janes consulting
music by tom muller at
modernspacemusic.com
[Music]